<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>About | the forecaster</title>
    <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/tag/about/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://collindougherty.github.io/tag/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>About</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://collindougherty.github.io/media/icon_huab95def157338f74d8ed74c4d7fc7d51_16289_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/tag/about/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Pure Signal</title>
      <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/finance/about-pure-signal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://collindougherty.github.io/finance/about-pure-signal/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://collindougherty.github.io/finance/about-pure-signal/index.en_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Pure Signal. When I was in the midst of my college career, I became fascinated by the way stock markets and crypto markets moved. Like many of my other passions, trying to make sense of the seeming randomness enamored me. I share many of my insights here as I refine old methods and forge new ones. Assets don’t move randomly. Under the surface, if you look closely enough, you can distinguish the signal from the noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collin Dougherty is a senior undergraduate at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln studying mathematics and psychology. He is particularly interested in how data can be used in a wide variety of fields, including sports analytics, trading, and surveys. He works in the field of sports analytics with the University of Nebraska. Learn more about Collin &lt;a href=&#34;https://collindougherty.github.io/&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About The Forecaster</title>
      <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/featured/about-the-forecaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://collindougherty.github.io/featured/about-the-forecaster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to The Forecaster, home of Collin Dougherty&amp;rsquo;s data driven insights (and occasional rambles). On the site you can find a host of different topics covered, including stock markets, cryptocurrencies, baseball, football, basketball and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I seek to use data and statistical machine learning to derive useful insights in all of these topics and more, whether it be a stock market trade idea or a prediction for a team&amp;rsquo;s performance in March Madness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I encourage you to check out my Twitter, where I post much more frequently and on an even wider variety of topics. My articles often make the most sense in that context. Check it out &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CollinD0ugherty&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collin Dougherty is a senior undergraduate at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln studying mathematics and psychology. He is particularly interested in how data can be used in a wide variety of fields, including sports analytics, stock trading, and more. He worked in the field of sports analytics with the University of Nebraska. Learn more about Collin &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/collin-dougherty/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
