<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bitcoin | Collin Dougherty</title>
    <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/tag/bitcoin/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://collindougherty.github.io/tag/bitcoin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Bitcoin</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://collindougherty.github.io/media/icon_huc338727306c0da16d008a2d3758f82ed_5456_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Bitcoin</title>
      <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/tag/bitcoin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracking My Bitcoin Trading Journey</title>
      <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/post/tracking-my-bitcoin-trading-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://collindougherty.github.io/post/tracking-my-bitcoin-trading-journey/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://collindougherty.github.io/post/tracking-my-bitcoin-trading-journey/index.en_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As Bitcoin breaks all time highs and prices above 60k begin to feel normal, many are asking if they should begin their Bitcoin journey. The answer is a resounding yes. There are many reasons to buy Bitcoin. I hope to lay out some of my favorite reasons at some point in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I am starting a new journey of my own, dabbling a bit into trading. I won’t be using a significant amount of capital, as I hope to learn on the fly. For most people, trading is unnecessary. Buying and holding will do. I am a hodler at heart myself. But in the interest of learning more about what drives short term price action and my desire to try my hand at day trading have led me to this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to update this post regularly with my trades and a brief explanation of why I am predicting a given short term price action. I may also post some of my options trading. In the interests of privacy and also because I am primarily trading a small amount at first, I will scale everything to a hypothetical initial investment of $10,000 USD. As I go, I hope to learn new things and devise new methods that will help better predict price action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for joining me. I hope my insights prove useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/25/2021: I began the process of trading today, sending my initial investment to Kraken. Again, I will be tracking a hypothetical investment of $10,000, based on the returns on my trades. So from this point forward, I will refer to my account balance with respect to the hypothetical $10,000 initial capital, as is standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had some interesting price action this morning. While my funds were not transferred in time to sell, we saw a spike in MACD and overbought levels on the RSI. I’ll bide my time in the meantime. Short term price action looks generally positive. We had a strong retest of the EMA (the exponential moving average, seen as the blue line below), and have since bounced well short term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Screenshot%20(31).png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be watching for the next sell signal, though I will not be surprised if we see continued positive price momentum over the near term, and I remain highly bullish on the current state of the market, fully expecting all time highs in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current Account: $10,000 (+0.00%)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
