<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Psychology | Collin Dougherty</title>
    <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/tag/psychology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://collindougherty.github.io/tag/psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Psychology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://collindougherty.github.io/media/icon_huab95def157338f74d8ed74c4d7fc7d51_16289_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Psychology</title>
      <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/tag/psychology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I got free from online distractions (and you can too)</title>
      <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/featured/tech-freedom/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://collindougherty.github.io/featured/tech-freedom/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The title of this post sounds rather self-congratulatory, but that’s not really my aim here. Rather, I have noticed an increasing trend among my peers of complaining about the large amount of time they spend on their phones, and, having spent quite a bit of time thinking about these issues myself, felt compelled to share some things that have worked for me. I find that the comments from friends are generally at the point of resignation, and it’s challenging to present ideas in a way that don’t come across as self-congratulatory. Nonetheless, the changes I have made have made a profound impact on me for the better and I desire for others to have the same opportunity if they so desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-problem&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think most people need to be given a rationale for why they should spend less time on screens, but I will touch on a few thoughts I have that may be novel to folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem I see with screens is closely linked to dopamine. As I touched on in a previous post, by interspersing high dopamine activities like social media throughout the day, we sabotage our ability to appreciate smaller pleasures like reading a book or chatting with a friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another huge problem is the ease with which screens enable boredom avoidance. Humans fundamentally hate boredom - even more than expending effort - and many useful creations in the world have come about from people who were bored and decided to do something interesting to alleviate it. Boredom avoidance itself is not the problem, but how we direct our energy is, and screens enable us to turn off boredom instantaneously and without effort, hijacking our dopaminergic pathways and our willingness to expend effort to attain rewards. Worst of all, screens prevent us from going to more constructive activities like reading a book, working on a hobby, or any number of things on that list of ideas we tell ourselves we will do “someday”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think most people need convincing that screens are generally a problem, and there are many arguments for this that have been documented in popular media. Our problem is that we feel helpless to do anything to change. Thus, I’ll lay out a few things that have worked for me. Everyone is different, and you have to buy in to your own system for it to be effective, but hopefully this can generate some ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;solutions&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Solutions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn your phone into a productivity device, not a distraction device&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re like me and most people, your phone is the biggest distraction problem. It’s simply the most accessible. Plus, those apps look so much better on mobile than desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook found years ago that something like 90% of their user minutes were coming on mobile, and that’s where big tech focuses their attention engineering efforts (which, incidentally is why browser versions suck).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One implication of this is that controlling your phone gets you 90% of the way to distraction freedom. Removing the distractions from your phone is a modern analogy for not keeping dessert in the house when you’re trying to cut down on sweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me this means deleting every social media, YouTube, and even limiting safari to a limited number of minutes a day (for when I’m really desperate to look up something on the go). I think that’s a pretty good start, but I would also strongly suggest removing any app that isn’t strictly necessary for day to day existence. This is a bit more extreme and can be a longer term goal, but I find that once you’ve removed the big distractions, removing some smaller ones is a logical next step. For me I’m essentially down to phone, messages, chatGPT, a couple productivity apps and a handful of built in apple apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people of course have tried this, I’m far from the first to suggest it, but I think building in failsafes for your future self’s inevitable moments of weakness is the key to long term success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One failsafe I’d recommend is getting a friend or family member to set a screen time password for you on the apps that are particularly problematic before you delete them. I have limits on instagram, X, etc, even though they are deleted from my phone, and my sister has the password. This makes it quite an effort to open these apps (for longer than your limit), even if I were to redownload them. I’d recommend setting the limit to something like 1 minute a day, or else consider something like Freedom for more flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these measures still fail, I recommend blocking the app store (so that you can’t redownload distractions) for certain hours of the day using Freedom, which is my next recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get an app &amp;amp; browser extension like Freedom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting your phone under control is only step 1, however. If you’re like me, you’ll soon find that even poorly engineered browser based social media is still quite addictive, and you’ll likely desire to put up guardrails for your PC based browsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I love Freedom for this task. It allows you to block sites and apps that you choose, and offers a locked mode which, once active, prevents even you from opening those distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that, while drastic and often annoying, I’d much rather be short term misaligned with my desires, and long term aligned, than the other way around. Eventually, you’ll stop even trying to open the sites that used to steal days from your existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve found particular success in having the schedule start relatively early in the morning, and it being active 6 days out of the week. This enables me to access any distractions I need, but forces me to either wait until my free day on Saturday (which I set to have no blocking) or else to wake up a bit earlier than I’d prefer. Almost all days I’d rather get an extra hour of sleep than scroll social media, so I just end up not on it at all, which I consider a win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, it took me about a month to get down this system, and I’d recommend being conservative with what you block in locked mode at first. It’s always easier to add more to your block list than to have to wait 24 hours for something you shouldn’t have blocked in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find your weak points and enact backup measures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally found that I was surprisingly good at finding loopholes that enable me to get around my own system (which is hilarious btw), so I’ve had to do a lot of plotting in my wiser moments to prevent myself from doing what I feel like in my dumber moments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things like having the App Store blocked for most of the day on my phone, having someone else with the screen time password, and using blocking software have been hugely effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusions&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, these ideas, rather than giving you a system to copy and paste, have helped you think logically about how to change your tech use for the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my part, as constricting as this all sounds, I have come to enjoy it, and on Saturday’s without any of these measures often become quickly overwhelmed by the distractions and crave the simpler existence of Sunday-Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On those days, I often get bored. Boredom turns out to be a much more common feeling than I’m used to, but its inspired me to do bigger things, from reading well known literature, to gaining knowledge in fields that interest me and overall having more freedom to follow my curiosity than ever before. Simply knowing that you’ve managed to gain 4-6 hours a day enables you to relax and follow your passions, which often lead to cool and useful things anyways. Successful change with tech has also given me momentum to eat healthier and think logically about behavior change more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past few months I’ve seen my screen time on my phone drop to under an hour most days (usually just iMessages), I’ve stopped streaming tv shows (except on Saturdays), have had significantly more focus on work and find my mind wandering to interesting new topics and ideas instead of reaching for my phone impulsively. In fact, this very blog post arises from an environment without distractions. 6 months ago I would’ve been watching a tv show or scrolling twitter instead of writing. In short, my life has radically changed for the better within only a few months, and the compounding effects I suspect will be even more substantial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, these changes aren’t for everyone, and I have no judgement for that. I only hope that people can live in alignment with what they aspire to, and if these tools help others with similar goals to mine, then that’s more than worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maslow..? Maslow..? Maslow..?</title>
      <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/featured/hedonic-treadmill-habituation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://collindougherty.github.io/featured/hedonic-treadmill-habituation/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The Hedonic treadmill. Habituation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how our brains are designed to function. There’s a logical reason for this in that constant seeking usually improves our survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I find its existence less interesting than its implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are always going to return to your hedonic baseline, then you should probably make the baseline as automatic as breathing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern societies don’t function this way. In order to maintain our baseline of happiness we require a big house, green lawn, beautiful driveway, perfectly painted rooms, interior decoration, the best streaming platforms, social media, alcohol, paid time off, vacations, a constantly changing personally curated playlist of songs that specifically appeals to our unique mental makeup…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this before any of the important psychological dimensions of being a human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have all these perks and are less happy than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people think the lower levels of Maslow’s hierarchy of needs are fulfilled today like never before. But what if we have just redefined the lower levels of the pyramid to require more than ever?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what would happen if we set a new baseline?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it possible that with a new baseline, you would come to appreciate the taste of healthy food, or the intrinsic joy in meaningful work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minimalist movement gets some of this right, but doesn’t go nearly far enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to re-baseline your technology usage, your free time, your definition of work and what you eat and drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some will say this is missing out on the best of modern society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t disagree more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By re-baselining, you free yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By becoming free, the perks of the modern world become wonders once more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Incentives of Academia are Broken</title>
      <link>https://collindougherty.github.io/featured/incentives-of-academia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://collindougherty.github.io/featured/incentives-of-academia/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;“It is not from the benevolence of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker, that we expect our dinner, but from their regard to their own interest.” -Adam Smith, Wealth of Nations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Captain John Smith and the Virginia Company settled Jamestown in 1607, they were not primarily a band of farmers, hunters, and explorers. Most were upper class adventurers with no experience in procuring their own survival. The first winter in the New World was a brutal lesson for them all in human psychology and motivation. Because the food supply was communal - everyone was guaranteed a meal - few planted, hunted or did any of the requisites for survival away from the luxuries of civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-thirds of the 120 men died that winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this, Smith instituted a famous rule: “he who will not work will not eat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;85% of the men survived the following winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such is a lesson in the power of negative punishment. But there is an equally important lesson in positive reinforcement from colonial times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Struggling to turn a profit for the holders of their joint-stock company, the Virginia Company turned to tobacco, a product of the new world, and instituted a policy supported by the Crown which granted 100 acres of land to any freeman who would settle in Virginia. On account of this incentive, thousands flocked to the new world, making themselves and their investors exceedingly wealthy, and ensuring the survival of the colony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans follow incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s turn our attention to the incentives of scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;College students go to graduate school, often because they don’t know what to do with their degree in the real world of producing goods and services. Or perhaps to make some more money on account of specific knowledge they can acquire with higher education. Or because they have invested so much time in schooling already that they can’t think beyond the next test and degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to graduate this institution of higher education, you are generally expected to submit a work of research - a thesis. After a life of simply regurgitating knowledge someone else taught them, students have no clue how to do anything truly new. So they do something slightly different from what everyone else in their field is doing. This reasoning by analogy leads to a culture of incrementalism that pervades scientific research from graduate school to tenure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many incentives for this behavior. The number of publications to your name are tantamount. But doing something truly new is a risky business. You can spend years working on new ideas that never become worthy of publication. Funding is also harder to acquire. Even more so without a track record of doing novel research. So you get a pareto distribution of production while the vast majority of scientists produce only incremental research that adds little value to human knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond this, the incentives are stacked towards publication in a journal that only a tiny percentage of the population is allowed to read. Journals are incentivized to make money, which they do from subscriptions that only universities can afford. Scientists, in order to have their work considered prestigious, rely not on actual substantive zero-to-one step changes in knowledge, but rather acceptance by a high enough quality journal. This enables justification of tenure, funding, promotion, industry connections, social status, or whatever motive is top of mind at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say nothing of the increasing trend towards misapplication of the precautionary principle in all areas of society, not just research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should add that I think most of the scientific community sees these problems, which is tremendously encouraging. I also have tremendous respect and excitement for the open science movement, although there are certainly still some problems to figure out. But the problems are fundamentally one of incentives. Solve the incentive problem and you solve all the other problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incentives as they stand clearly do not align with maximizing human flourishing through scientific advancement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without scientific advancement there can be no technological advancement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without technological advancement there can be no economic advancement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without economic advancement, there can be no positive-sum games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without positive-sum games there can be no liberty.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
